Hi everybody, today's דף daf is כ"ח. Kaf-Chet. We pick up on
כ"ז עמוד ב' Chaf-Zayin Amud-Bet and God willing this שבת Shabbos we
will do two דפים dapim so we will be back on track.
So we pick up on כ"ז עמוד ב', Chaf-Zayin Amud-Bet, middle of
page, two dots. רבי יהודה אומר אין ביעור חמץ אלא שריפה. Rabbi
Yehuda omer ein biyur chametz ela sreifa. So after a really fascinating
four to five דף, daf, a very focused and extended, I don't
know if you could say both those words at the same time,
but anyway, discussion on aspects of איסורי הנאה issurei hana’ah and where
we learn them from and whether they are considered related to אכילה,
achilah, not related to אכילה, achilah, שלא כדרך הנאתן. shelo kederach hana’atan.
The specific issue that we dealt with yesterday was what things constitute
הנאה: hana’ah: visual, smell, visual no, smell yes. And then yesterday we
got to the focused discussion about
the specific discussion about הנאה hana’ah that comes from wood and whether
that's coming from the wood or coming from the ashes and how
that also links to the idea that
many things even after they become ashes remain forbidden. It's only things
that there's a מצות שריפה mitzat sreifa when they become ashes that
they become permissible. And now we turn to this issue by חמץ,
chametz, whether—oh welcome back Seth—whether by חמץ chametz the מצוה mitzvah is
to burn it or the מצוה mitzvah is to destroy in some
other means. Thank you. And this is the debate of רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda and the חכמים. Chachamim. So let's take a look. רבי
יהודה אומר אין ביעור חמץ אלא שריפה. Rabbi Yehuda omer ein biyur
chametz ela sreifa. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says the only way to
destroy חמץ chametz is by burning it. Okay. And the end of
the משנה mishnah of that משנה mishnah is וחכמים אומרים מפרר וזורה
לרוח. vachachamim omrim mefarer vezoreh laruach. You can crumble it and throw
it to the wind, או זורק לים o zorek layam you throw
it into the ocean. But רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you have
to burn it. So let's see why. Now let me just ask
you, what things have we learned already in the last few days
that you have to burn?
What
about this ערלה orlah stuff?
ערלה, orlah, כלאים, kilayim, although ערלה's orlah questionable where we know it
from, כלאים kilayim there's a classic דרשה drasha פן תקדש תוקד אש.
pen tikdash tukad eish. And then more specifically in the תורה Torah
is burning נותר. nosar.
So the question becomes, and I mentioned this because you know it
gets to that heart of where do we learn that things are
forbidden in הנאה? hana’ah? And some things are forbidden in הנאה hana’ah
you have this הקדש hekdesh paradigm, if you remember, specifically things that
it doesn't say אכילה achilah and that it's more about completely taboo
and even לא כדרך הנאתה lo kederach hana'atah and related to the
whole הקדש hekdesh paradigm is the idea that you burn it, what
you do with פסולי המוקדשים psulei hamukdashim and what you do with
נותר. nosar. חמץ chametz as we know is אסור בהנאה assur behana’ah
based on אכילה achilah and nevertheless, according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
it is something that it is similar that you burn it and
destroy it and that it has this completely taboo type of a
identity to it. So let's take a look at that.
שור הנסקל? shor haniskal?
שור הנסקל shor haniskal you bury, you don't burn. The only things
you burn are basically הקדש hekdesh and עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Although
עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, yeah I mean עבודה זרה avodah zarah even
the ashes afterwards remain אסור, assur, but עבודה זרה avodah zarah and
כלאים kilayim and so on so let's take a look at this.
רבי יהודה אומר אין ביעור חמץ אלא שריפה. Rabbi Yehuda omer ein
biyur chametz ela sreifa. So תניא, tanya, we taught in a ברייתא.
braita. אמר רבי יהודה אין ביעור חמץ אלא שריפה. amar Rabbi Yehuda
ein biyur chametz ela sreifa. The only way you can destroy חמץ
chametz is by burning it. והדין נותן vehadin noten and the logic,
you know, argues for this. It's compelling logic, right. ומה נותר שאינו
בבל יראה ובל ימצא, u-mah nosar she'eino be-val yeira'eh u-val yimatze, נותר
nosar you're not over on, you don't transgress the prohibition of you
shall not see and shall not be found, נותר nosar in your
house, טעון שריפה ta'un sreifa you burn it. חמץ שישנו בבל יראה
ובל ימצא, chametz sheyeshno be-val yeira'eh u-val yimatze, חמץ chametz that you
do transgress, לא כל שכן שטעון שריפה, lo kol sheken sheta'un sreifa,
how much more so should you have to burn it?
Now the
problem is, now there's a logic to relate the two, right? If
the idea is you can't even have it around, it really emphasizes
as I would sort of say, you know, the taboo nature of
it, the complete detaching yourself from it so that sense of like
destroying it, you can't even be in your possession, connected to a
concept of destroying it and שריפה, sreifa, there's a certain logic to
it.
But נותר nosar you do transgress the prohibition of having left it
over. So if anything it's less of a קל וחומר kal vachomer
and more of an analogy. The same way נותר nosar you transgress
and you left it over and now what you have to do
with it is you burn it so there's a transgression and that
more problematizes the object and now you burn it, חמץ chametz also
there's a transgression. On the other hand I should point out that
maybe this is why he makes it a קל וחומר kal vachomer
that you destroy חמץ chametz before you've transgressed. Whereas נותר nosar you
don't destroy before you've transgressed. But then the logic in connecting it
to בל יראה ובל ימצא bal yeira'eh u-val yimatze is less clear
because you destroy it so as not to transgress בל יראה ובל
ימצא bal yeira'eh u-val yimatze but not because you've transgressed. I mean,
so anyway, actually the הלכה halacha is that if it's actually—if it's
פסח Pesach itself, if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says
דאמרינן בפרק קמא. de'amrinan be-perek kama. first wide line in רש"י Rashi
לרבי יהודה le-Rabbi Yehuda אבל בשעת ביעורו השבתתו בכל דבר aval be-sha'at
bi'uro hashpatato be-khol davar that you destroy it by שריפה sreifah ערב
פסח, erev Pesach, but once it becomes פסח, Pesach, you get rid
of it anyway possible. So it's actually interesting that it is not
an analogy to נותר. notar. נותר notar you transgress and then you
burn it, whereas חמץ chametz you burn it according to רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda before you transgress so that you won't transgress.
Okay, so it's problematic to learn from קדשים kodashim because קדשים kodashim
is מעילה. me'ila.
I understand, so don't worry, the גמרא Gemara knows all those arguments,
but let's start with just pointing out the logic and the analogy
here. Okay, so he's making it as a קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
אמרו לו, amru lo, the Rabbis said back to him, כל דין
שאתה דן תחילתו להחמיר וסופו להקל אינו דין. kol din she'ata dan
techilato le-hachmir ve-sofo le-hakel eino din. Any קל וחומר kal vachomer you
make because הלא דין, halo din, דין din has a technical meaning
of a קל וחומר kal vachomer and you see that he said
it's, you know,
כל שכן kol shekein by חמץ. chametz. So they said any קל
וחומר kal vachomer you make that starts out being stringent, says okay,
you got to use only burn, nothing else, but in the end
it winds up being lenient, so it's not a קל וחומר kal
vachomer because it's not a real stringency, in the end it's a
leniency. What type of leniency is there by burning חמץ? chametz? לא
מצא עצים לשרפו, lo matza etzim le-sarfo, if you can't find wood
to burn it, יהא יושב ובטל? yehei yoshev u-vatel? What,
you should do nothing? And basically you're telling the guy if you
can't burn it, you don't have to do anything, you're an אונס.
oness. So really? Really he's going to get off from an obligation
to burn?
והתורה אמרה תשביתו שאור מבתיכם,
ve-ha-Torah amra tashpitu
se'or mi-bateikhem, the תורה Torah says get rid of חמץ chametz from
your house בכל דבר שאתה יכול להשביתו, be-khol davar she-ata yakhol le-hashpito,
any way you can get rid of it. Now the second point
seems to be less of questioning the
קל וחומר kal vachomer and more of just saying the פסוק pasuk
is very generic. But it also seems that the argument is, you
know, when you say destroy it in any way, in a sense
we're being lenient on you that we're giving you many options. But
in another sense we're being very insistent and strict in ensuring that
you have that you do everything possible to make sure that there
is no חמץ chametz in your house. And if you limit me
in one way and say I have to burn it, then in
a way you're also alleviating my responsibility if that's not a reasonable
option. So the Rabbis say there's another way of looking at this,
that we're being more stringent in demanding that you do every option
possible, any means possible of getting rid of the חמץ. chametz. And
they also might just say it's the פשט pshat of the פסוק
pasuk implies to get rid of it in any way possible. So
that's their counterargument. I should also point out that that idea that
חומרות chumros very often lead to קולות kulos is very important, you
know, and everybody always assumes that חומרות chumros come at no cost,
you just might as well be מחמיר. machmir. And there so often
are קולות kulos that come out of it, קולות kulos in terms
of בין אדם לחברו, bein adam le-chaveiro, to קולות kulos in terms
of how it impacts our family, חומרות chumros in terms of even
other, even like, you know, מצוות בין אדם למקום mitzvos bein adam
la-makom that there are very often a lot of tradeoffs involved in
being מחמיר machmir and things are not cost-free חומרות. chumros. So anyway,
that's what the חכמים chakhamim say, this is not just a חומרא,
chumra, it's a קולא. kula. So חזר רבי יהודה ודנו דין אחר.
chazar Rabbi Yehuda ve-danu din acher. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda went
back and he made a different type of a derivation and this
is less of a קל וחומר kal vachomer and more of an
analogy. נותר אסור באכילה וחמץ אסור באכילה. notar assur be-akhila ve-chametz assur
be-akhila. You can't eat נותר, notar, you can't eat חמץ. chametz. Now
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you can't eat חמץ chametz already, we're
going to discuss this a little bit later today, that you can't
eat חמץ chametz already starting in the sixth hour, right already starting
from חצות chatzos of the day before, which is the time, and
that we assume everybody agrees to, and that's the time when you
burn חמץ. chametz. So even though you haven't transgressed yet by חמץ,
chametz, the point I made before, nevertheless it still is off limits.
It's forbidden in eating starting by midday and נותר notar is forbidden
in eating.
So מה נותר בשריפה אף חמץ בשריפה. ma notar be-sreifa af chametz
be-sreifa. So the same way you burn נותר, notar, you burn חמץ.
chametz. Now that's a היקש. heikesh. Yes, היקש, heikesh, well that's what
it said, which is an analogy. Okay, now of course that's a
little wild if you say that, we should start burning everything you're
not allowed to eat. So the גמרא Gemara says back, so מה
נותר בשריפה אף חמץ בשריפה. ma notar be-sreifa af chametz be-sreifa. אמרו
לו, amru lo, the Rabbis said back to him, נבילה תוכיח, neveila
tochiach, which is essentially their response. How about נבילה, neveila, right, a
carcass of an animal, an animal that wasn't שחט-ed, shecht שאסורה באכילה
ואינה טעונה שריפה. she-asura be-akhila ve-eina te'una sreifa. You can't eat and
you don't have to burn it, as is the case with most
things you can't eat. אמר להן, amar lahen, he said back to
them, הפרש, hefresh, there's a difference. נותר אסור באכילה ובהנאה notar assur
be-akhila u-va-hana'ah וחמץ. ve-chametz. By the way, you'll notice that this is
an unusual, I mean, that it's an extended discussion of תנאים tannaim
and it's all in Hebrew, right,
very often when the גמרא Gemara says he would say this and
then he would say that back, it's the אמוראים Amoraim saying what
the תנאים tannaim would say and there's a lot of ארמית. Aramaic.
Here it is an extended discussion of תנאים tannaim which you normally
don't have, because normally it's just here's my הלכה, halakha, here's your
הלכה. halakha. Here it's a debate about how we derive it from
the פסוקים, pesukim, and you get some interesting locutions and some interesting
like הפרש, hefresh, you know, there's a distinction. Is this what they
actually said? Yes, right. So this, anyway, but this is just to
point that out. No, there's a distinction. נותר אסור באכילה ובהנאה. notar
assur be-akhila u-va-hana'ah. Not saying it applies to anything אסור באכילה. assur
be-akhila.
I'm saying about things that are totally off limits. You can't eat
and you can't derive. הנאה. hana'ah. Those are things you burn. וחמץ
אסור באכילה והנאה v'chametz assur b'achila v'hana'ah and חמץ chametz is the
same. מה נותר טעון שריפה אף חמץ טעון שריפה. ma nosar taun
sreifa af chametz taun sreifa. The same way you burn נותר, nosar,
you burn חמץ. chametz. So אמרו לו, amru lo, so now anybody
who's been learning with us the last few days knows that there
are some things that are אסור בהנאה assur b'hana'ah you don't have
to burn. שור הנסקל יוכיח, shor haniskal yochiach, right? The ox that
you gore will be the counterproof. שאסור באכילה ובהנאה, she'assur b'achila u'v'hana'ah,
you can't eat or derive benefit and ואין טעון שריפה, v'ein taun
sreifa, you don't burn it. אמר להן, amar lahen, he said back
to them, הפרש, hefresh, there's a difference. נותר אסור באכילה ובהנאה ויש
בו כרת. nosar assur b'achila u'v'hana'ah v'yesh bo karet. It's really taboo,
off-limits. Number one, you don't get הנאה. hana'ah. Number two is that
if you eat it, you get כרת. karet. So clearly it's seen
as this completely taboo thing. וחמץ
אסור באכילה ובהנאה ויש בו כרת. v'chametz assur b'achila u'v'hana'ah v'yesh bo
karet. מה נותר בשריפה, ma nosar b'sreifa, the same way you burn
נותר, nosar, אף חמץ בשריפה. af chametz b'sreifa. So that seems like
a pretty good proof. And again, there's a compelling logic there, right?
The more something is completely taboo and off-limits and I might even
sort of say like evil, okay maybe that's putting it a little
bit too far but okay, you know, but certainly there's that
whole you know sort of השקפי hashkafic way of looking at חמץ,
chametz, associate don't own it, don't have it, destroy it, don't get
benefit from it. So you know the idea of burning it is
a certain you know there's a certain connection there. So we see
that by נותר nosar and we see it by חמץ. chametz. So
אמרו לו, amru lo, so what are they going to say back
to them? חלבו של שור הנסקל יוכיח. chelbo shel shor haniskal yochiach.
The fat of a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, which is very tricky
because it's the שור הנסקל shor haniskal aspect of it that is
the הנאה hana'ah and the חלב chelev aspect that's the כרת, karet,
and they happen to intersect but it's not really in itself has
both elements. Okay, שאסור באכילה ובהנאה, she'assur b'achila u'v'hana'ah,
you can't eat or derive benefit because it's part of a שור
הנסקל, shor haniskal, ובו כרת v'bo karet and you get כרת karet
because of the חלב chelev part, but there's no one איסור issur
that has all components. But anyway, ואין טעון שריפה v'ein taun sreifa
and you don't have to burn it. So surprisingly he does not
respond to that. He goes in a different tack, but seems to
me that that's a pretty weak argument. This feels like a מדרש
הלכה. midrash halacha. This is right, so this is like a מכילתא.
mechilta.
This is exactly, this is a מדרש הלכה midrash halacha but even
as a because they're discussing derivation from פסוקים pesukim but it's not
exactly, because even a מדרש הלכה midrash halacha it's rare that it's
this extended back and forth and back and forth. And it's also
different because a מדרש הלכה midrash halacha and I have to find
if you have this type of a you know debate in a
מדרש הלכה midrash halacha because right, because a מדרש הלכה midrash halacha
starts with a פסוק. pasuk. So therefore the shift is no, the
פסוק pasuk is telling you something else. Whereas this starts with debating
the law and they're bringing different פסוקים pesukim and different arguments to
prove the law. So in that way it has a different anchoring
and center than a מדרש הלכה. midrash halacha. Interesting.
The reason why I said it actually was I was trying to
imagine where this literary unit originally sourced and I said to myself
תשביתו שאור מבתיכם, tashbitu se'or mibateichem, right, right, so
it seems to be a מדרש הלכה midrash halacha on that
פסוק pasuk
transposed and embedded here.
I agree. I have to look, I didn't, I should have, I
have to look in the מדרש הלכה midrash halacha to see like
in the מכילתא mechilta if they have it. I would not be
surprised if they have a snippet of it. But again the reason
I think it's unusual even for it certainly is similar to מדרש
הלכה midrash halacha in that it's spending a lot of time talking
about the derivation and not just different הלכתי halachic opinions. A classic
משנה mishna and ברייתא braita is to use an academic word apodictic,
which means, which means like you know here's the law period. It's
a simple declarative statement, this is the law, this is the law,
it's not like an argument back and forth and discussion and so
on. But so but
and it doesn't focus on פסוקים, pesukim, and this focuses on פסוקים.
pesukim. On the other hand, מדרש הלכה midrash halacha says I learn
this from the פסוק, pasuk, you might have a brief response, but
then we go on saying what else we learn from the פסוק.
pasuk. Here their concern is what is the law and trying to
prove what is the law going back and forth which is more
of a משנה mishna type of a concern. So it's an interesting
question you know whether this actually is rooted like you know would
be an extract from a מכילתא. mechilta. But it certainly comes from
the world of the world of focusing on derivation as opposed to
just focusing on sort of the law itself. Okay so let's take
a look. חזר רבי יהודה chazar Rabbi Yehuda top of כ''ח עמוד
א'. kaf ches amud aleph. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda went back
ודן דין אחר v'dan din acher and he tried another way of
deriving it. נותר ישנו בבל תותירו וחמץ בבל תותירו. nosar yeshno b'val
toisiru v'chametz b'val toisiru. So this is more of the analogy rather
than the קל וחומר kal vachomer argument. That the idea of the
similarity of נותר nosar and חמץ chametz in addition to הנאה hana'ah
and כרת karet which seemed pretty compelling argument, there's also this sense
of sort of not letting it happen or you know preventing, you
know again which sort of speaks to getting rid of the phenomenon.
So you're not supposed to let נותר nosar be left over and
חמץ chametz you're not allowed to leave over meaning to have it
in your house once it becomes once it becomes פסח. Pesach. Of
course again the irony is as I said that רש''י Rashi points
out that once you've transgressed by חמץ... chametz... and it is פסח,
Pesach, רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda doesn't limit himself to שריפה. Sreifah. But
nevertheless, the point is that by both of them, you maybe could
have said חמץ ישנו במצות תשביתו, Chametz yeshno be-mitzvahs tashpitu, but the
same idea here that both of these things you're not supposed to
encounter them, you're not and and you're supposed to get rid of
them, and again, it's another argument for that analogy. Okay, so it
says מה נותר בשריפה mah notar b'sreifah and therefore the same way
you burn שריפה, sreifah, אף חמץ בשריפה af chametz b'sreifah you burn
חמץ. chametz. אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said back to him, אשם
תלוי וחטאת העוף הבאה על הספק לדבריך יוכיחו. asham talui v'chatat ha-of
haba al hasafek l'devarecha yochichu. Now you probably weren't expecting that. So
he says, ah, according you have a different פסק הלכה psak halacha
somewhere in קדשים Kodshim that actually undermines or is an exception to
the argument you're making. Why? You have a position that an אשם
תלוי, asham talui, an אשם תלוי asham talui is a sin offering
somebody brings by a sin that were they to know they did
it inadvertently, they would bring a חטאת. chatat. But they don't know
they did it. They might have done it. And actually, there's a
basis to say they did do it. For example, a classic classic
case is you have two pieces of forbidden fat in front of
you. One is forbidden fat and one is permissible fat and you
ate one of those pieces and you don't know which one you
ate. So there's a very concrete objective reality that you might have
transgressed. Okay, but you don't know which one you ate. So in
that case you bring an אשם תלוי, asham talui, a suspended אשם,
asham, it's suspending your sin until you can determine whether you have
to bring a חטאת chatat or not. That's case number one. Case
number two is חטאת העוף הבאה על הספק. chatat ha-of haba al
hasafek. Normally you don't bring a חטאת chatat if you have a
doubt. You bring an אשם תלוי, asham talui, you don't bring anything.
But but sometimes you bring a חטאת chatat not for sin but
for purification purposes. And a classic example is a woman who has
a child, she has to bring a חטאת chatat in order that
she can once again eat קדשים. kodshim. Okay, it's part of the
purification process. A bird sin offering, a bird חטאת. chatat. Now, let's
say she has a miscarriage and she doesn't know if it was
a viable child or not. So what can she do? If she
doesn't bring the חטאת, chatat, she'll never eat קדשים kodshim again. If
she brings the חטאת, chatat, well maybe she's not obligated and then
the כהנים kohanim can't eat a bird חטאת chatat that was not
a real sacrifice because you do מליקה, melikah, you do with the
fingernail from the back of the neck, it's a נבילה neveilah if
it's not a real sacrifice. So there's a special category called חטאת
העוף הבאה על הספק, chatat ha-of haba al hasafek, which actually, which
the גמרא Gemara understands from tradition is what you do have the
option of bringing it, but then the כהנים kohanim don't eat the
bird, they just go ahead and destroy it. So how do you
destroy a אשם תלוי asham talui that became invalid, either was left
over, נותר notar or טמא tamei or whatever, or a חטאת העוף
הבאה על הספק? chatat ha-of haba al hasafek? Now you would assume
that it was like all other קדשים kodshim that you have to
destroy because they're invalid or whatever, which is you burn it. That
we know is the הלכה halacha by קדשים. kodshim. But the Rabbis
say, 'Aha! But you actually have a unique position here and say
you don't burn these things.' So according to you, your whole idea
that there should be a general rule that things that you're not
allowed to have and etc. you have to burn, this gives lie
to it. What do you do? Okay, so let's let's take a
look. שאנו אומרים בשריפה, She'anu omrim b'sreifah, we say you have to
burn it, ואתה אומר בקבורה, ve-attah omer b'kevurah, you say you bury
it. So שתק רבי יהודה, shatak Rebbe Yehuda, he was silenced, he
didn't have a response. Now by the way,
based on your own position, you've got yourself into a corner. According
to us, you would have had a good argument, but because of
your weird position here, now you—now of course the funny thing is
is that these things, they fit in with the earlier analogy that
they're אסור בהנאה asur b'hana'ah and ענוש כרת enosh karet and all
those types of thing because they're קדשים. kodshim. But according to the
most recent analogy of ישנו בבל תותירו, yeshno b'val totiru, that doesn't
exactly apply to the חטאת העוף הבאה על הספק. chatat ha-of haba
al hasafek. Of course you could always wait till it becomes a
day old and etc. But anyway, so it's not exactly relevant to
the most—as directly relevant to the most recent analogy, but it certainly
is more relevant to the earlier analogies and they say this doesn't
fit if you're trying to make a general rule that you burn
these types of things.
So
אמר רב יוסף, amar R' Yosef, so רב יוסף R' Yosef said,
היינו דאמרי אינשי, hainu d'amri inshi, this is what people say, כפא
דחט נגרא, kafa d'chata nagra, the ladle that the carpenter cut
out, carved out, בגוויה נשרף חרדלא, begava nishraf chardala, with it he
basically burnt his tongue on mustard. So meaning like you did it
to yourself. So אביי אמר, Abaye amar, and אביי Abaye gave another
little like saying, סדנא, sadna, the also like the carpenter or whatever
or the person that made the
stockade, בסדנא יתיב, besadna yatev, he has to wind up sitting in
his own stockade. If he went ahead and broke the law, they'll
put him in the stockade that he himself made.
Exactly, you cooked your own goose.
Right, or to quote Shakespeare, that's right, Shakespeare hoisted by his own
petard. So מדולי ידיה משתלם, midvelei yadei mishtalem, he is paid back
from the action of his own hands. Hoisted by his own petard.
רבא Rava אמר amar גירא, gira, the arrow maker, גירא מכתו, gira
michto, kills himself with his own arrows. מדלי ידיה משתלם, Midlei yadei
mishtalem, he is paid back with the action of his own hands.
So that's nice.
Gloating? What? Gloating? It's fun. It's like, oh, wasn't that interesting? Oh,
that was good, he got himself with that. So I don't think
they're gloating over that they won it out of him, but it's
like
it's humorous. It's teasing, right. Anyway, so that raises an interesting question
of how we פוסקין, pasken, because if it weren't for his other
position by the חטאת העוף, chatas ha'ov, actually he would have had
a good argument. And if we rule against him by the חטאת
העוף, chatas ha'ov, maybe he does have a compelling position. So there's
a very interesting מחלוקת ראשונים machlokes rishonim if we rule like רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda or not. Big debate in ראשונים rishonim whether we
rule like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, whether we rule like the חכמים
chachamim about אין ביעור חמץ אלא שריפה. ein bi'ur chametz ela s'reifa.
I want to talk, get to the משנה mishnah and then I
want to say a very important conceptual point about this debate.
So there's downside actually to burning it.
Right, which is why we do burn it, but again, if you
don't have that option. So now let's take a look at the
חכמים. chachamim. חכמים אומרים chachamim omrim מפרר וזורה לרוח, mefareir ve'zoreh laruach,
you crumble it and throw it to the wind or you throw
it into the ocean. איבעיא להו, Iba'u lehu, they raised the question,
היכי קאמר, heichi ka'amar, which way what are the חכמים chachamim saying?
מפרר וזורה לרוח, mefareir ve'zoreh laruach,
you crumble it and זורה, zoreh, by the way, I point out
it's not זורע zoreia with an ע, ayin, it's זורה, zoreh, which
is like winnow, scatter it to the winds, do you crumble it
and scatter it to the winds or ומפרר מטיל לים, umepareir matil
layam, or you crumble it and throw it to the ocean. So
the word crumble goes on both options. או דלמא, O dilma, or
do we say, no. מפרר וזורה לרוח, mefareir ve'zoreh laruach, if you're
going to throw it to the wind, you got to crumble it,
because what are you going to do, take a loaf of bread
and throw it to the wind? It falls to the ground and
then somebody else will eat it. So if you're going to just
throw it to the wind, you have to crumble it. אבל מטיל
לים בעיניה, Aval matil layam be'inei, but if you're going to throw
it into the
ocean, go throw it in in its own thing. Didn't we have
that in our משנה? mishnah? Our משנה mishnah is pretty
clear, it says אף מפרר וזורה לרוח או מטיל לים. af mepareir
ve'zoreh laruach o matil layam. Right, but the question is is מפרר,
וזורה לרוח mefareir ve'zoreh laruach, או מטיל לים, o matil layam. or
is it מפרר mefareir, וזורה לרוח, או מטיל לים. ve'zoreh laruach o
matil layam, That's the way one would read it. It's a completely
reasonable read. Completely reasonable read. But why do they
care so
much?
Because they want to know what you do. If I find חמץ
chametz in my house, here's the classic modern-day זורה לרוח. zoreh laruach.
What would you tell me
to do if I find חמץ chametz in
my house? Flush it
down the
toilet. Flush it down the toilet. That's the classic מטיל לים. matil
layam. Do I have to crumble it before I flush it down
the toilet? You don't want it to get stuck. Yeah, well let's
say it's not. All right, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
Okay, so ותנן נמי גבי עבודה זרה כי האי גוונא. u'tenan nami
gabbei avodah zarah ki hai gavna. We have a similar משנה mishnah
by עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yosei omer, what
do you do if you find עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? שוחק וזורה
לרוח או מטיל לים, shocheik ve'zoreh laruach o matil layam, you grind
it up and throw it to the wind or you throw it
into the ocean. ואיבעיא, ve'iba'u, so the question is שוחק, וזורה לרוח
shocheik ve'zoreh laruach, או מטיל לים o matil layam. or is
it שוחק וזורה לרוח, shocheik ve'zoreh laruach, או מטיל לים. By the
way, I should point out that this is clear that עבודה זרה
avodah zarah is not בשריפה. bi'sreifa. I mean it does say אשריהם
תשרפון באש, ashereihem tisrefun ba'eish, but anyway, well the חכמים chachamim agree
they just have a different position, whatever, we'll see. ואיבעיא להו, ve'iba'u
lehu, and we raise the question, היכי קאמר, heichi ka'amar, which way
is he saying? שוחק וזורה לרוח ושוחק ומטיל לים, shocheik ve'zoreh laruach
u'shocheik u'matil layam, grind it because obviously you're not talking about bread,
you're not talking about crumble, you're talking about something more like out
of metal or wood, so you grind it up and throw it
to the wind or grind it up and throw it to the
ocean. או דלמא, O dilma, or do we say, שוחק shocheik, וזורה
לרוח, if you're going to throw it to the wind, grind it
up, אבל מטיל לים בעיניה, aval matil layam be'inei, throw it into
the ocean just the way it is.
אמר רבה, amar Rabbah, מסתברא, mistavra, it makes sense, that maybe there's
a difference between עבודה זרה avodah zarah and חמץ. chametz. עבודה זרה
דלים המלח קאזיל, avodah zarah de'leyam hamelach ka'azal, when we speak about
עבודה זרה avodah zarah and throwing it to the ocean, we always
say throw it into the ים המלח. yam hamelach. Why? Because the
ים המלח, yam hamelach, on one hand you could say things float
in the ים המלח, yam hamelach, they don't sink, but
on the other hand, nobody uses the ים המלח, yam hamelach, nobody
traverses it. So therefore it's clearly out of the reach of people.
So if you're going to throw things to the ים המלח, yam
hamelach, לא בעי שחיקה, lo ba'i shechika, you don't have to grind
it because even if it's not ground and you have a little
idol floating in the ים המלח, yam hamelach, nobody's going to come
across it. חמץ דלשאר נהרות קאזיל, chametz de'lishar naharot ka'azil, חמץ chametz
that we just say throw to the ocean, any ocean, any body
of water, so people might come across it. So in that case
בעי פירור, ba'i pirur, you have to crumble it in order that
a loaf of bread might wash off might wash. All right, so
that's what רב יוסף Rav Yosef was going to say. So that's
what רבה Rabbah says. אמר ליה רב יוסף, amar lei Rav Yosef,
אדרבה, adrabba, the opposite, איפכא מסתברא, ippcha mistavra, the opposite makes sense.
עבודה זרה דלא ממיאיסה, avodah zarah delo mami'isa, עבודה זרה avodah zarah
that does not become soggy and disgusting,
בעי שחיקה, ba'i shechika, you have to grind it up even by
the ים המלח, yam hamelach, who knows, somebody might come across it
as a nice pristine idol. So that's a problem, you got to
grind it up wherever you're putting it. חמץ דממיאיס, chametz de'mami'is, חמץ
chametz that becomes dissolved, becomes soggy and dissolved, לא בעי פירור, lo
ba'i pirur, it doesn't need to be crumbled. So basically anywhere you
throw it it'll be dissolved and it's not a problem. Okay, תניא
כוותיה דרבא *Tanya k'vatei d'Rava*. What, let's get to the משנה Mishnah.
*mishna*. תניא כוותיה דרבא *Tanya k'vatei d'Rava*, תניא כוותיה דרב יוסף *Tanya
k'vatei d'Rav Yosef*. We have a ברייתא braita. *braita* supports each position.
תניא כוותיה דרבא *Tanya k'vatei d'Rava*, we ask according to, we have
a ברייתא Braisa *braita* like רבא *Rava*. האי מהלך במדבר מפרר וזורה
לרוח *Hai mehalech bamidbar mefarer v'zoreh laruach*, האי מהלך בספינה מפרר ומטיל
לים *Hai mehalech bisphina mefarer u'metil layam*. So we have a ברייתא
*braita* that says explicitly by חמץ chametz *chametz* because of the use
of the verb מפרר *mefarer*, that if you're going in the wilderness
you crumble it and throw it to the four winds and if
you're going in the ocean you crumble it and throw it into
the ocean. So explicitly says it by חמץ chametz. *chametz* you crumble
like רבא *Rava*. תניא כוותיה דרב יוסף *Tanya k'vatei d'Rav Yosef*, and
we have a ברייתא *braita* like רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* that says
you always grind up עבודה זרה *avodah zarah*. האי מהלך במדבר שוחק
וזורה לרוח *Hai mehalech bamidbar shochek v'zoreh laruach* and you throw it
to the wind. האי מהלך בספינה שוחק ומטיל לים *Hai mehalech bisphina
shochek u'metil layam*, you grind and throw it into the ocean. So
basically now what we would have said is that they're both wrong.
You see from the ברייתות *braitot* that the right read of the
משנה Mishnah *mishna* is that you always grind it. But that's not
the conclusion that we're going to come to. So you have evidence
that according to that you know to both sides but they argue
that at least sometimes you don't have to grind it. So how
will they define their defend their position? שחיקה קשיא לרבא *Shchika kashya
l'Rava*. Grinding the עבודה זרה *avodah zarah* is a challenge for רבא
*Rava* because רבא *Rava* said you don't have to grind עבודה זרה
*avodah zarah*, you throw it into the ים המלח Yam Hamelach. *Yam
HaMelach*. פירור *Pirur* and crumbling חמץ chametz. *chametz* is קשיא לרב יוסף
*kashya l'Rav Yosef*, is a challenge for רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* who
said you never have to crumble because it always gets soggy. So
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says שחיקה לרבא לא קשיא *shchika l'Rava lo
kashya*. Grinding עבודה זרה *avodah zarah* is not a challenge to רבא
*Rava*. הא בים המלח הא בשאר נהרות *Ha b'Yam HaMelach ha b'shear
neharot*. רבא *Rava* says no no no, I said that because we
assume you're throwing it into the Dead Sea by עבודה זרה *avodah
zarah* you don't have to grind it but you're allowed to throw
it into other bodies of water, when you do that then you
have to grind it. So רבא *Rava* says I don't really in
principle argue with רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*, this is the way תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafot* says. I just said, רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*, this is
the way תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* explains it, רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* assumed
you were throwing the עבודה זרה *avodah zarah* into other seas and
therefore he said grind it. I said that no normally we mean
the Dead Sea and then you don't have to grind it, but
yes when you do do it into any other sea you would
grind it and that's the case of grinding the עבודה זרה *avodah
zarah*. פירור לרב יוסף לא קשיא *Pirur l'Rav Yosef lo kashya*. Now
how would why would רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* say you would have
to crumble the bread if he says it normally gets soggy? הא
בחיטי הא בנהמא *Ha bechiti ha benahama*. It's a difference between are
you dealing with bread or wheat. Bread you get soggy you don't
have to worry it gets disgusting, wheat might not get disgusting and
therefore now the question is I don't get it like grinding wheat
why would you have to grind wheat and turn it into flour
I mean it's every little pieces of wheat just wouldn't that be
enough to just scatter it? So רש"י *Rashi* says no what the
only thing here it means by crumble is not literally crumble. It
means don't put a the wheat all in a bag and throw
a bag of wheat into the ocean because then that'll get preserved.
So what you do is you scatter the wheat kernels that's effectively
like crumbling it. Okay so they have this debate it basically boils
down to if you throw a loaf of bread you know are
you afraid that it'll wash up you know or do you say
even if it does it'll be too soggy and we don't have
to worry about it.
Now they do not consider the געבראכטס *gebrochts*, right, that's right.
Now I wanted to say Charlie had a question, yes, oh געבראכטס
*gebrochts* is a much later מנהג *minhag*.
But now there are people in Israel who maintain you can't drink
the water because people tossed their beer cans into the reservoir
and חמץ chametz *chametz* isn't בטל *batel* even במשהו *b'mashehu* and whatever.
Okay fine I'm not going to answer that right now.
Well this this would seem to make that argument ridiculous.
Well yes but they but I don't think they had they don't
think they desalinated their river drinking water I think they got their
water from wells although I don't know I mean maybe they got
some of their water from rivers so and this does say נהרות
*neharot*. This includes נהרות *neharot* right anyway whatever so. So I want
to say something about this debate. We פסקן *pasken* it's a מחלוקת
ראשונים *machloket rishonim* we don't have a clear פסק *psak*. But what's
clear and this is a conceptual point that רב חיים Reb Chaim
*Rav Chayim* makes a beautiful little short רב חיים הלוי *Rav Chayim
HaLevi* on the רמב"ם *Rambam* about this debate of רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* and the חכמים Chachamim *chachamim*. What's clear from the
חכמים Chachamim *chachamim* is that it's not just a question of a
different of modes of destroying because if you think about the point
about what's being emphasized by the חכמים *chachamim* the concern is right
will it other people wind up encountering it right but not that
have you actually destroyed the object. Think about the עבודה זרה *avodah
zarah* that you threw into the ים המלח *Yam HaMelach* without grinding
up. If you ask me did I destroy it it's with a
focus on the object the answer is no. What did I do?
I got it out of the reach of people okay. And the
same seems to be the concern here by חמץ chametz *chametz* not
technically do we say this act constitutes destroying but is it effectively
getting it away from people. So רב חיים *Rav Chayim* says that
that actually because he he's working off of a טור *Tur* and
the טור *Tur* says if you burnt your חמץ chametz, *chametz* the
are the ashes מותר בהנאה mutar behanaah. *mutar behana'ah* or אסור בהנאה
assur behanaah. *assur behana'ah*. So he says well according if we rule
according to those ראשונים *rishonim* that rule like רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
*Rabbi Yehuda* the ashes are מותר בהנאה *mutar behana'ah*. According to those
that say you destroy it anyway the ashes are אסור בהנאה assur
behanaah. *assur behana'ah*. So רבי עקיבא איגר *Rabbi Akiva Eiger* says he
says I don't understand. The whole reason we say ashes are מותר
בהנאה is cause of the principle of, as we discussed before, נעשה
מצותו. na'aseh mitzvato. You did the מצווה mitzvah that you were supposed
to do with this object. So here, even according to the חכמים
that say you destroy it anyway, there’s still a מצווה mitzvah to
destroy it. It’s not just a convenience of getting it away. There’s
a מצוות תשביתו. mitzvat tashbitu. So you did the מצווה mitzvah through
burning it, so it’s נעשית מצותו. na'aseit mitzvato. The ashes should be
permissible. Why is there a difference? Either way, there’s a מצווה mitzvah
to destroy it. And רב חיים says there's no, there's a big
difference. If the מצווה mitzvah is to burn it, then because the
תורה Torah is focusing on a very specific act, burning, then the
concern of the תורה Torah is a specific act done to this
object. An act of burning done to this object, and therefore was
the act done to the object? Yes, the מצווה mitzvah was done.
When it says get rid of it anyway, the תורה Torah doesn't
really care what you do with the object. It's not concerned about
a specific type of an act. What the תורה Torah is concerned
about is if it says get rid of it anyway you can,
what's the תורה's Torah concern?
Notice the word I even used. Get rid of it, not destroy
it anyway you can. Get rid of it anyway you can. And
the concern is that your חמץ chametz be out of your possession,
out of your house, unavailable. And there’s not an idea of doing
an act to this particular object. It is an idea of getting
rid of the חמץ. chametz. And that's what he says is the
concern. And you see that again I think even in the idea
that you don't even have to really destroy the חמץ. chametz You
just have to make it completely out of reach. Okay, and you
throw it into the ים המלח. And that really is a very
important conceptual distinction. It's not just a question of technically is it
about שריפה sreifah or is it about something else? Yes, but the
fact that we don't, that there are options other than that is
what I’m using to demonstrate that that’s not really the conceptual point
there. Okay, so let’s now look at the next משנה. Mishnah. חמץ
של נכרי שעבר עליו הפסח. chametz shel nochri she'avar alav haPesach. We’ve
been talking about your חמץ Chametz being אסור בהנאה. assur behanaah? Now
we’re dealing about חמץ Chametz owned by a non-Jew that פסח Pesach
passed over. מותר בהנאה. You can derive benefit of it. I mean,
nobody did any עבירה, aveira, it’s no longer פסח, Pesach, גזונטערהייט. gezunterheit.
ושל ישראל אסור בהנאה. veshel Yisrael assur behanaah. So now, of course,
the elaboration of the first half has to be a discussion of
the question about חמץ שעבר עליו הפסח. chametz she'avar alav haPesach. Right?
Let’s say it was... so, not the first half, the second half.
Right? Now is if it’s a Jew’s and it’s no longer פסח,
Pesach, so it’s חמץ שעבר עליו הפסח, chametz she'avar alav haPesach, the
Jew transgressed, it’s אסור בהנאה. assur behanaah. שנאמר לא יראה לך שאור.
shenemar lo yeira'eh lecha se'or. You can’t see שאור. se'or. What does
that have to do with it being אסור בהנאה? assur behanaah, But
the juxtaposition, the implication is since you as a Jew transgressed owning
חמץ, Chametz, as a consequence after פסח Pesach it remains אסור בהנאה.
assur behanaah, Rabbinically or biblically. We know it’s rabbinic, but we will
see there are those that say it’s even biblical. So let’s take
a look now at the גמרא. Gemara The גמרא Gemara says like
this: מאני מתניתין? mani matnitin? Who’s our משנה going like? לא רבי
יהודה ולא רבי שמעון ולא רבי יוסי הגלילי. lo Rebbi Yehuda velo
Rebbi Shimon velo Rebbi Yosi HaGelili. Neither רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda. or
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon or רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rebbi Yosi HaGelili, meaning
the three תנאים Tannaim we know that debate when חמץ Chametz. is
אסור בהנאה, Assur Bahana'ah. none of them fit the משנה. מאי היא?
mai hi? Where are you getting this from? דתניא, detanya, it’s taught
in a ברייתא. חמץ בין לפני זמנו ובין לאחר זמנו, chametz bein
lifnei zemano uvein le'achar zemano, whether before its time, meaning from midday
on ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, so it’s a מצווה mitzvah to destroy
it but it’s not yet פסח, Pesach, or whether after the time,
after פסח, Pesach, עובר עליו בלאו. over alav belav. Then you transgress
a negative prohibition if you eat חמץ. Chametz. However,
תוך זמנו, toch zemano, on פסח, Pesach, עובר עליו בלאו וכרת. over
alav belav vekares. You transgress a negative prohibition and כרת, kares, and
you get כרת. kares. So the only difference between before and after
is that on פסח Pesach you get כרת, kares, after you transgress
without getting כרת. kares. דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rebbi Yehuda. That’s what
רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda. says. רבי שמעון אומר, Rebbi Shimon omer, top
of כח עמוד ב. kaff chet amud bet. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
says, חמץ לפני זמנו ולאחר זמנו אינו עובר עליו בלאו כלום. chametz
lifnei zemano ule'achar zemano eino over alav belav klum.
Before and after the time you don't transgress nothing, anything. תוך זמנו,
toch zemano, on פסח, Pesach, עובר עליו בלאו וכרת. over alav belav
vekares. Then clearly of course there’s a negative prohibition and כרת. kares.
Now the question is, does רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon literally mean you
don't transgress anything? We’ve been working with this universal assumption that biblically
you can’t eat חמץ Chametz on ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, right? I
mean the גמרא Gemara spoke about a מצווה mitzvah of תשביתו, tashbitu,
but we've assumed that also biblically, I mean the גמרא's Gemara always
assumed that from midday it’s even אסור בהנאה, Assur bahana'ah right? So
what תוספות Tosafot says is that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon does not
mean that you can eat it ערב פסח. Erev Pesach. But he
agrees that there’s a מצווה mitzvah of תשביתו, tashbitu, and a corollary
of a מצווה mitzvah of תשביתו tashbitu is don’t eat it. Okay,
but it’s not like a negative prohibition. It’s not like לא תאכל
חמץ. lo tochal chametz. Okay, it’s not a clear לאו, lav, and
there’s no איסור הנאה. issur hanaah. It’s just a corollary of the
מצווה mitzvah of תשביתו. tashbitu. Okay, now you remember I assume that
we spoke about like if even a person tries to marry a
woman with, you know, חיטי קורדנייטי. chitei kordanaiti. right, this idea that
ערב פסח Erev Pesach not only is there a מצווה Mitzvah of
תשביתו, Tashbitu, not only can't you eat it, but it's even אסור
בהנאה. Assur bahana'ah? So far that's just רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda רבי
שמעון Rebbe Shimon says not only after פסח, Pesach, which we take
for granted is there no biblical prohibition, even before פסח Pesach all
you have is תשביתו Tashbitu and maybe a corollary of don't eat
it because of תשביתו, Tashbitu, but you certainly do not have an
איסור הנאה. Issur Hana'ah. That is רבי שמעון. Rebbe Shimon. Okay. ומשעה
שאסור באכילה אסור בהנאה. U’misha'ah she'assur b'achilah, assur b'hana'ah. From the moment
it's forbidden in eating, you can't get benefit. The גמרא Gemara so
now the גמרא Gemara interjects, אתאן לתנא קמא Atan l'Tanna Kamma that
line goes back to רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda Because רבי יהודה Rebbe
Yehuda says from the moment you can't eat it, from midday of
ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, you also can't get הנאה, Hana'ah, which is
the position we're familiar with. רבי שמעון, Rebbe Shimon, as we just
said, said that from midday maybe you're not allowed to eat it
because of תשביתו, Tashbitu, but it's not forbidden in הנאה. Hana'ah. Okay.
So now we have what we take for granted right now is
a hybrid of רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda and רבי שמעון. Rebbe Shimon.
The רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is the position of איסור הנאה Issur
Hana'ah from midday, but after פסח, Pesach, רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda also
says it's אסור Assur biblically. So there we assume like רבי שמעון,
Rebbe Shimon, that after פסח Pesach it's not biblically prohibited. But right
now we see that רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda says both are biblical
and רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says no, neither are biblical. So those
are those two positions. רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר, Rebbe Yossi HaGlili omer,
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbe Yossi HaGlili says תמה עליך, Tmah alecha, you
should be astounded about
yourself, your assumption that it's אסור בהנאה Assur bahana'ah? on פסח. Pesach.
הי חמץ אסור בהנאה כל שבעה? He chametz assur bahana'ah kol shivah?
Who makes you think that even on פסח Pesach it's אסור בהנאה?
Assur bahana'ah. Talk about sort of shattering our world view. So he
says where do you get this idea that even on פסח Pesach
it's אסור בהנאה? Okay.
Would he mean that rhetorically?
What? No, he means it literally. He means it literally. ומניין לאוכל
חמץ משש שעות ולמעלה שהוא עובר בלא תעשה? U’minayin l'ochel chametz misheish
sha'ot u’l'ma'alah she'hu over b'lo ta'aseh? Now, where do you
so that's point number one. Before so one says neither before nor
after, the other says both before and after, and רבי יוסי הגלילי
Rebbe Yossi HaGlili says even during it's not אסור בהנאה. Right. ומניין
לאוכל חמץ
משש שעות ולמעלה שהוא עובר בלא תעשה? U’minayin l'ochel chametz misheish sha'ot
u’l'ma'alah she'hu over b'lo ta'aseh?
Now, where do you know this is according to רבי יהודה Rebbe
Yehuda, who says by midday it's already אסור באכילה. Assur b'achilah. Where
do you know that that's true, that there's a biblical negative prohibition?
שנאמר, Shene'emar, the פסוק Pasuk says, לא תאכל עליו חמץ. Lo tochal
alav chametz. Don't eat חמץ Chametz on it, meaning on the קרבן
פסח, Korban Pesach, from the time you can bring the קרבן פסח.
Korban Pesach. דברי רבי יהודה. Divrei Rebbe Yehuda. That's what רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says. So now the ברייתא here is not focusing exactly
on the הנאה Hana'ah right now, it's focusing on this question of
whether there's a לאו, Lav, a negative prohibition to eat from midday.
And רבי יוסי Rebbe Yossi doesn't address that, right?
Right, רבי יוסי Rebbe Yossi doesn't address that. So Eli said, we've
assumed totally like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda? there's a negative prohibition and
איסור הנאה. Issur Hana'ah. Now we're seeing, no, that's רבי יהודה'ס Rebbe
Yehuda's position. רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says there's not even a negative
prohibition, maybe it's a corollary of תשביתו Tashbitu not to eat it,
but it's not even a negative prohibition. So what's רבי שמעון Rebbe
Shimon going to do with the פסוקים? Pesukim? So אמר לו רבי
שמעון, Amar lo Rebbe Shimon, so רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon said back
to him, וכי אפשר לומר כן? V’chi efshar lomar kein? Can you
really say that? That that's what the פסוק Pasuk means? והלא כבר
נאמר, V’halo kvar ne'emar, and that you biblically you can't eat from
midday? והלא כבר נאמר, V’halo kvar ne'emar, the פסוק Pasuk says, לא
תאכל עליו חמץ שבעת ימים תאכל עליו מצות. Lo tochal alav chametz,
shivat yamim tochal alav matzot. The end of the פסוק Pasuk is
seven days eat מצות. Matzot. You want to say עליו Alav means
the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, so it starts from midday. I'll point
out to you that the end of the פסוק Pasuk parallels it
to the whole holiday of פסח Pesach of חג המצות Chag HaMatzot
and the whole seven days, which is not ערב פסח. Erev Pesach.
So אם כן מה תלמוד לומר לא תאכל עליו חמץ? Im kein
mah talmud lomar lo tochal alav chametz? So what's the emphasis on
"on it," which from which you emphasized the time קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach is brought from midday? And I say that can't be. So
I say בשעה שישנו ב"קום אכול מצה" ישנו ב"בל תאכל חמץ". B’sha'ah
she'yeshno b'kum echol matzah, yeshno b'bal tochal chametz. To tell you the
opposite. Not that the prohibition of חמץ chametz. starts from the time
of bringing the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach from midday ערב פסח. Erev
Pesach. The opposite, to tell you the מצווה Mitzvah of מצה Matzah
applies as long as there's a prohibition of חמץ, chametz which means
always. What does so let's take a look what this means.
בשעה שישנו ב"קום אכול מצה" ישנו ב"בל תאכל חמץ". B’sha'ah she'yeshno b'kum
echol matzah, yeshno b'bal tochal chametz.
So when there is the מצווה Mitzvah of eating מצה, Matzah, there's
a prohibition of eating חמץ. chametz? ובשעה שאינו ב"קום אכול מצה" אינו
ב"בל תאכל חמץ". U’v’sha'ah she'eino b'kum echol matzah, eino b'bal tochal chametz.
When there's no מצווה Mitzvah of eating מצה, Matzah, there's no prohibition
of חמץ. chametz So basically, actually what I sort of said was
more what I said the wrong way, I was actually accidentally jumping
ahead, I'm sorry, I was jumping ahead to a different point. So
I'm sorry, I was jumping ahead. He does what I said he'll
do in a minute, but he hasn't done it yet. So he
says, no, I say you say you focus on the עליו Alav
and say חמץ chametz? begins when פסח Pesach begins and for you
פסח Pesach begins means the bringing of the פסח ערב פסח. Pesach
Erev Pesach. I focus on the end of the פסוק, Pasuk, not
the לא תאכל עליו, Lo tochal alav, but the שבעת ימים תאכל
עליו מצות. Shivat yamim tochal alav matzot. And I say that חמץ
chametz. only begins when מצה Matzah begins. And therefore it begins on
פסח Pesach itself. It does not begin, there's no prohibition ערב פסח.
Erev Pesach.
And so you're permitted מדאורייתא, m'de'oraisa, you can eat
it, get הנאה, hana'ah, if you eat it, according to the way
תוספות Tosafot frames it, you would not be עובר over on a
negative prohibition, but you would have counteracted the מצוה mitzvah of תשביתו.
tashbisu. Okay, that's the way he understands, because he brings clear evidence
that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you can't just take your time
eating it during ערב פסח. Erev Pesach. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon can't
take your time eating it during mid-day. Okay, so okay, so that's
what he says, but that it's all linked, it's linked to מצה
matza and it only starts on פסח Pesach itself. So מאי טעמא
ד רבי יהודה? mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Yehuda? So הגמרא hagmarah says, you
know, it's a reasonable argument. הפסוק hapasuk isn't clearly saying ערב פסח,
Erev Pesach, it could very reasonably be read only on פסח Pesach
itself. So what's the position of רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda, תלתא קראי
כתיבי, tilsa k'ra'ei k'sivi, there's three פסוקים: pesukim: לא יאכל חמץ, lo
ye'achel chametz, 'chametz should not be eaten'; כל מחמצת לא תאכלו, kol
machmetzes lo socheilu, don't eat any even crumb, scrap of bread; לא
תאכל עליו חמץ, lo sochal alav chametz, don't eat chametz. It says
it three times. חד לפני זמנו חד לאחר זמנו וחד לתוך זמנו.
chad lifnei zemano, chad l'achar zemano, v'chad l'soch zemano. One to tell
you before its time, one during its time, and one after its
time. The three prohibitions tell you that it's prohibited before פסח, Pesach,
on ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, on פסח, Pesach, and after פסח. Pesach.
תוספות Tosafot by the way, as we pointed out, he also assumes
an איסור הנאה, issur hana'ah, and תוספות Tosafot points out since one
of them says לא יאכל, lo ye'achel, even according to חזקיה Chizkiya
who needs לא יאכל, lo ye'achel, that teaches that all the others
are a similar prohibition. That's how תוספות Tosafot understands. But three פסוקים
pesukim anyway tell you before, during, and after. That's where רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda gets it from. רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, what does רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon do? I mean, התורה hatorah does repeat multiple times
don't eat חמץ. chametz, What's each one doing for him? חד לתוך
זמנו. chad l'soch zemano. Obviously, the main one is to tell you
don't eat it during פסח. Pesach. וכל מחמצת, v'kol machmetzes, how about
הפסוק hapasuk that says if any, you know, even any crumb of
bread don't eat? מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, mibaya lei l'chidetanya, it's to tell
you another הלכה. halacha. A הלכה halacha we taught in
הברייתא. habraisa. אין לי אלא שנתחמץ מאליו, ein li ela shenischametz me'elav,
I only know something that's called חמץ chametz. if it ferments by
itself. מחמת דבר אחר, machamas davar acher, if it fermented because of
some external fermenting agent, מניין, minayin, how do I know that's called
חמץ? chametz. תלמוד לומר כל מחמצת לא תאכלו. talmud lomar kol machmetzes
lo socheilu. Because כל מחמצת kol machmetzes means like the, you know,
I think the הפעיל hif'il means something that was, you know, caused
to become חמץ chametz? is how he's reading it and not just
something that ferments by itself. Now, what caused it to become חמץ?
chametz. So something could ferment in two ways. Normally, it could ferment
because you just leave it out with the flour and the water
and it will ferment, or you could put in yeast or sourdough.
So תוספות Tosafot says no, there was never א הוה אמינא a
hava amina that sourdough would be, you know, שאור se'or would make
something less חמץ. chametz. That's like classic חמץ, chametz a שאור. se'or.
So clearly שאור se'or gets mixed up with with flour, of course
it makes it חמץ. chametz There's no question. תוספות Tosafot says no,
what we mean is other fermenting agents that are not sourdough. So
first of all, what's yeast? Isn't yeast yeast is just a bacteria,
right? But what's sort of the medium that they're in? But what's
what's the medium that that bacteria is in? Some anyway, but anyway,
but you could do you could create like a fermenting agent by
like תוספות says like, you know, he he actually describes how they
make bread and he says like you take the the peels of
grapes, you know, because they have sugar or whatever and the bacteria,
you know, sort of grow on it and you can use that
as a fermenting agent. So תוספות says that's the question when you
use it's flour and water but the fermenting agent is not it
doesn't ferment by itself and it's not sourdough, it's some other type
of fermenting agent.
Baking powder, right, baking powder, baking powder or those little bags of
yeast would be considered to be חמץ. chametz.
Well, by themselves no, but something that became bread that fermented because
they were added, yes. We normally say, right, that when does something
become חמץ? chametz You leave it out for 18 minutes. But that's
an amount of sort of fermenting on its own. If I throw
in a little yeast, it's even less than 18 minutes. So let's
say what I did was I threw in a little baking powder,
waited less than 18 minutes and put it in the oven. So
it fermented, but not on its own. And there he says maybe
that would not be considered
חמץ. chametz, What?
So yeast isn't חמץ.
chametz Yeast that's not sourdough, right, non-sourdough based yeast.
Or also on those little yellow and red envelopes.
Look, I don't know if the way they make yeast actually in
that packet has some flour and water that was mixed up with
it. Okay, but if you actually could have pure laboratory, you know,
yeast fermenting whatever, that is not. But you mix it with flour,
that is חמץ chametz and we learn that from כל מחמצת. kol
machmetzes. Okay, so that's what we learn from כל מחמצת. kol machmetzes.
Okay, so now לא תאכלו. lo socheilu.
So תלמוד לומר כל מחמצת לא
תאכלו. talmud lomar kol machmetzes lo socheilu. He says like this, אין
לי אלא שנתחמץ מאליו. ein li ela shenischametz me'elav.
כל מחמצת לא תאכלו. kol machmetzes lo socheilu. לא יאכל חמץ, lo
ye'achel chametz, how about the third one? What do you need that
for? Since for him האיסור ha'issur is only on פסח Pesach itself.
מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, mibaya lei l'chidetanya, like we taught in הברייתא. habraisa.
רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר מניין לפסח מצרים, Rabbi Yossi HaGlili omer minayin
l'Pesach Mitzrayim, רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGlili but for a different
purpose, not the idea we were saying before. How do you know
that the פסח Pesach that they had in מצרים... Mitzrayim... which was
before they had a חג המצות, Chag HaMatzot, when they just had
פסח, Pesach, the קרבן, korban, but they didn't yet have the holiday,
the יום טוב Yom Tov of חג המצות, Chag HaMatzot, שאין חימוצו
נוהג אלא יום אחד? she'ein chimutzo noheig ela yom echad? How do
you know for there that the prohibition of חמץ chametz, was only
one day, which is basically like it's חג המצות Chag HaMatzot that
makes a seven-day prohibition of חמץ. chametz When they just had a
קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, look, when you bring פסח Pesach on פסח
שני, Pesach Sheini, you're allowed to have חמץ chametz, in your house.
So therefore on the first day, on the first day of the
actual first פסח, Pesach, he says yes, the Torah says don't eat
חמץ, chametz but that wasn't related to a holiday. That was a
one-day prohibition. So תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, how do you know it?
תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, לא יאכל חמץ, lo yei'achel chametz, חמץ chametz
should not be eaten, is in the פסוק pasuk by the first
קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. וסמיך ליה, v'samich lei, and the next פסוק
pasuk says, היום אתם יוצאים, hayom atem yotzim, today you are going
out from Egypt. So the rabbinic read is לא יאכל חמץ היום,
lo yei'achel chametz hayom, don't eat חמץ chametz today. So that פסוק
pasuk is to tell you that. Now of course it's quite fascinating
because normally we need a פסוק, pasuk, if we're sort of arguing
what do you do with this פסוק, pasuk, what do you do
with that פסוק, pasuk, you need it to tell you a הלכתא
hilchata thing. Here we're telling you something purely historical, completely irrelevant to
הלכה. halacha. For them it was, but for us it has no
הלכה halacha relevance. But that's what you do with the פסוק pasuk
to learn that out. רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, now רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda who says each of those three פסוקים psukim is telling you
a different time: before, during, and after, how does he learn out
these other things? מחמת דבר אחר מנא ליה, machmat davar acher m'na
lei, where does he know that it's even a problem even if
it has an external fermenting agent? מדאפקה רחמנא בלשון מחמצת, m'dafpakei Rachmana
b'lashon machmetzet, because it—there's two things. A, it's an extra פסוק, pasuk,
and it could have said חמץ, chametz, but it chooses to use
the word מחמצת, machmetzet, so I learn two things: the extra פסוק
pasuk tells me a prohibition before the time, and the use of
the word מחמצת machmetzet tells me even externally fermented.
So Rabbi Lindsay, could you say something about the general principle that
you can't learn more than one thing from a פסוק? pasuk? In
other words, it to me it always
seems random. It's like when the חכמים want to learn more than
one thing, they're free to do so, and when they want to
constrain themselves and say you can only learn one thing, you use
the פסוק pasuk this way, you—it's not—it's used up. You can't use
it anymore.
There's no gas
in the tank of the פסוק.
pasuk. I think that—great question.
I think you'd have to show me examples of what types of
things you have in mind when you say they learn multiple things,
because here what they're learning out is from the sense that there
is redundancy, or that there
is—you know, we're learning something out because there's—it's extra. And so the—if
the basis of deriving a new law is the fact that this
is an extra פסוק pasuk or it's an extra word, an unusual
word, then if the basis is the redundancy, once it stops being
redundant you no longer have a basis to derive something. So that's
the assumption here. Now when you say they can learn multiple things
from a פסוק, pasuk, normally they're not basing themselves on a redundancy.
They have a complex פסוק pasuk and they say: this part teaches
this, that part teaches that, that part teaches that, but that's—but they're
not learning based on the redundancy, they're learning from each word they're
learning something. Here they're basically saying the whole thing is redundant, so
the redundancy teaches us something. So once you're using that redundancy to
teach something else, what's left to learn? Right? Exactly. Exactly. Okay, so
that's very helpful. Okay, good, glad. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. So how does he learn
out—so that's because of the use of the word מחמצת. machmetzet. So
how about the other הלכה? halacha? רבי יוסי הגלילי מנא ליה, Rabbi
Yossi HaGlili m'na lei, where does he learn out this point of
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGlili about the פסח מצרים, Pesach Mitzrayim,
the איסור חמץ issur chametz was one day? אי בעית אימא מדסמיך
ליה היום, i ba'it eima m'desamich lei hayom, a similar point. A,
you have an extra פסוק, pasuk, but B, you have another thing
to pay attention to, not just the redundancy, but the juxtaposition to
the word היום. hayom. So that can let us learn out that
point. ואי בעית אימא, v'i ba'it eima, and if you want I
could tell you, סמוכים לא דריש, smuchin lo darish, he doesn't at
all learn out anything from the juxtaposition and he disagrees with רבי
יוסי הגלילי. Rabbi Yossi HaGlili. Okay, so פסח מצרים Pesach Mitzrayim wasn't
just one day of איסור חמץ. issur chametz. Whatever. Okay, I don't
agree with it, it was maybe all seven days. Okay, which is
an interesting question: did they have a חג המצות Chag HaMatzot the
first—on the first time? Yeah, they were certainly traveling during that time.
Okay, now let's get back. אמר מר, amar mar, so quoting—going back
to what we said before: מניין לאוכל חמץ משש שעות ולמעלה שהוא
עובר בלא תעשה? minayin l'ochel chametz misheish sha'ot u'l'ma'ala she'hu over b'lo
ta'asei? How do you know, going back to the position of רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda that starting already midday you transgress a negative prohibition?
שנאמר לא תאכל עליו חמץ, she'ne'emar lo tochal alav chametz, it says
חמץ should not be eaten on it, דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi
Yehuda. Now we learned out that his דרשה drasha is not just
"on it" from the time the קרבן korban is being brought, but
also from the redundancy of the פסוק. pasuk. אמר לו רבי שמעון,
amar lo Rabbi Shimon, so רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said back to
him: וכי אפשר לומר כן? v'chi efshar lomar kein? Can you make
that argument? והלא כבר נאמר לא תאכל עליו חמץ שבעת ימים תאכל
עליו מצות. v'halo kvar ne'emar lo tochal alav chametz shivat yamim tochal
alav matzot. The פסוק pasuk says don't eat on it חמץ, seven
days eat מצות. matzot. So clearly the prohibition of חמץ starts when
the מצוה mitzvah of מצה matzah begins on פסח Pesach night, not
on ערב פסח. Erev Pesach. So the גמרא Gemara says, maybe it
was something I said. So the גמרא says, רבי יהודה שפיר קאמר
ליה רבי שמעון, Rabbi Yehuda shapir ka'amar lei Rabbi Shimon, רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon makes a very good argument. The פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* links
it to the מצוה mitzvah, *Mitzvah* of מצות *Matzah*. רבי יהודה אמר
לך *Rabbi Yehuda amar lach*, so רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* would say
back to you, ההוא לקבוע חובה אפילו בזמן הזה הוא דאתא *Hahu
lekavoa chova afilu bizman hazeh hu de'asa*. Yeah, this is I jumped
ahead when I said this before. That is to tell you the
linking to to מצות *Matzah* is not to tell you חמץ *Chometz*
only starts when מצות *Matzah* starts, חמץ *Chometz* only starts on פסח
Pesach, *Pesach* on on the night of of of the 15th. It's
to tell you the opposite, that מצות *Matzah*, the מצוה mitzvah *Mitzvah*
of מצות *Matzah* endures as long you know is is relevant as
long as the מצוה mitzvah, *Mitzvah* of חמץ *Chometz* is relevant, meaning
even nowadays. Even when there's no קרבן פסח Korban Pesach. *Korban Pesach*,
there still is a מצוה mitzvah *Mitzvah* of מצות *Matzah* as long
as you will have a prohibition of eating חמץ *Chometz*, you'll have
a מצוה mitzvah *Mitzvah* of eating מצות *Matzah*. So it's not to
tell you it's not that חמץ *Chometz* starts when מצות *Matzah* starts,
it's that מצות *Matzah* applies throughout all generations the same way חמץ
*Chometz* applies throughout all generations. Now, why would I have thought otherwise?
You would have thought otherwise if you were not steeped in our
already existing realities of the סדר *Seder* and you just read the
פסוקים psukim *Psukim*. Because if you just read the פסוקים psukim *Psukim*,
the פסוקים psukim, *Psukim* say two things. Number one they say שבעת
ימים תאכל מצות *Shivat yamim tochal matzos*, right? So if you read
that literally, you would have you'd be eating מצות *Matzah* make a
point of eating מצות *Matzah* every seven days of פסח Pesach, *Pesach*.
So alright there's a גר"א *Gra* says it's a קיום *Kiyum* to
do it whatever. But anyway, we generally assume that those פסוקים psukim
*Psukim* really mean that as an alternative to חמץ *Chometz*, if you
want bread, you can't have your bread, you can't have fermented bread,
have unfermented bread, but not that there's a מצוה mitzvah *Mitzvah* to
eat all seven days. Once it's not a מצוה *Mitzvah* to eat
all seven days, how do we know there's a מצוה *Mitzvah* to
eat at night? So בערב תאכלו מצת *Ba'erev tochelu matzos*. I wait
I will get to that. That is a דרבנן *D'rabonon* פסוק pasuk
*Pasuk* that's not a פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* in the תורה *Torah* actually.
Okay, I'll tell you in a minute. So if you look at
the פסוקים *Psukim*, all the פסוקים *Psukim* say is על מצות ומרורים
יאכלוהו *Al matzos umerorim yochluhu*. Other than seven days, the only thing
the פסוקים *Psukim* say is eat your קרבן פסח Korban Pesach. *Korban
Pesach* with מצות *Matzah* and מרור *Maror*. In that פסוק pasuk *Pasuk*,
מצות *Matzah* has no special role more than מרור *Maror*. It's an
accompaniment to the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach. *Korban Pesach*. So it's a
very reasonable question to ask that if you don't have a מצוה
*Mitzvah* all seven days, and you don't have a קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach, *Korban Pesach*, why would I think you have to eat מצות
*Matzah* ליל סדר *Leil Seder*? Okay, and therefore he says that's what
the פסוק *Pasuk* is telling me. It tells me that as long
as there's a מצוה *Mitzvah* of of of
an איסור *Issur* of חמץ *Chometz*, there's a מצוה *Mitzvah* of מצות
*Matzah*. And therefore there's it remains not all seven days, but at
least it remains the first night. That's what he learns. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says ורבי שמעון לקבוע חובה מנא ליה *VeRebbi Shimon lekavoa
chova minalei*? Where does he know that it's a מצוה *Mitzvah* even
nowadays? נפקא ליה *Nafka lei*, he learns it out from בערב תאכלו
מצת *Ba'erev tochelu matzos*. In the evening you should eat מצות *Matzos*.
So Michael's saying, yeah that's a great פסוק *Pasuk*, it says in
the evening eat מצות *Matzos*, why I mean why is there even
a question? And the answer is because that's not what the פסוק
*Pasuk* says. The פסוק *Pasuk* says שבעת ימים תאכלו מצת *Shivat yamim
tochelu matzos*, you should eat מצות *Matzos* for seven days. It says
it says what does it say?
you want this? Yeah, it says basically from the 14th at night
to the 21st what where where is the פסוק *Pasuk*?
י"ב *Yud Bet*.
Thank you.
Oh come on.
Okay,
I can't find anything here. I'm still in י"ב *Yud Bet*, no
I'm
in י"ג *Yud Gimmel*. בראשון בארבעה עשר לחדש בערב תאכלו מצת עד
יום האחד ועשרים לחדש בערב *Barishon bearba'ah asar lachodesh ba'erev tochelu matzos
ad yom ha'echad ve'esrim lachodesh ba'erev*.
Okay,
so
eat מצות *Matzos* from the night of the 14th until the night
of the 21st. So what we do is we basically just cut
off the end of the פסוק *Pasuk*, right? Rather than reading that
as the פשט *Pshat*, which is it's a seven-day מצוה *Mitzvah* to
eat מצות *Matzah*, which is what all the other פסוקים *Psukim* say,
we cut off we just focus on the first half. Eat on
the first night. Okay, anyway, that's what we learn it out of,
but it's not clear at all from the פסוקים *Psukim*. So now
the גמרא *Gemara* says ורבי יהודה מבעי ליה *VeRebbi Yehuda miba'ei lei*,
what does רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* do from בערב תאכלו מצת *Ba'erev
tochelu matzos*? Again, this issue of using the פסוק *Pasuk*. He needs
it to tell me לטמא ושהיה בדרך רחוקה *Letamei veshehaya bederech rechoka*.
That
that I would have not said immediately it applies even nowadays. I
would have said the מצוה *Mitzvah* of מצות *Matzah* applies only when
there's a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach. *Korban Pesach*, but it applies to
people even who are not eating a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach, *Korban
Pesach*, that they still have to eat מצות *Matzah*. Who are the
people that are not eating קרבן פסח Pesach, *Korban Pesach*? Somebody who
is טמא *Tamei*. No, when there's a בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, meaning
he would have said, I would not have initially said if I
just had the פסוק *Pasuk* בערב תאכלו מצת *Ba'erev tochelu matzos* that
it applies nowadays post מקדש Mikdash. *Mikdash*. I would have said it
applies when there's a מקדש Mikdash. *Mikdash*, but it applies to people
who don't eat קרבן פסח Pesach, *Korban Pesach*, like somebody who was
טמא *Tamei* and was or was in a far away place. סלקא
דעתך אמינא, I would have said הואיל ובפסח לא יאכל מצה ומרור
נמי לא ניכול, ho’il uve-Pesach lo yochal matzah umaror nami lo neichol,
since he doesn’t eat פסח, Pesach. he wouldn’t have a מצוה, he
wouldn’t maybe even be allowed, unless they wouldn’t have a מצוה to
eat מצה ומרור, matzah umaror, קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that
he does and that's the first step in making מצה ומרור matzah
umaror independent. But maybe I wouldn't have applied it post-מקדש. Mikdash, I
needed a second פסוק to apply it post-מקדש. Mikdash. רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, and רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, טמא ושהיה בדרך רחוקה, tamei veshehayah
bederech rechokah, לא אצטריך קרא. lo itztrich kra.
You don't need a פסוק to tell me that they eat מצה.
matzah. Why? דלא גרע מערל ובן נכר. delo gara me’arel uven neichar.
They wouldn't be different from an uncircumcised person, even if he was
uncircumcised due to no fault of his own, maybe his family has
hemophilia, or a בן נכר, ben neichar, which here does not mean
non-Jew, but means a person who has sort of rejected a מצוה,
sort of a מומר mumar for one thing.
ואנא ידענא ve’ana yadana that they already eat מצה matzah even if
they're not eating the קרבן פסח. How do I know it? דכתיב,
dechtiv, the פסוק says, וכל ערל לא יאכל בו, vechol arel lo
yochal bo, every ערל arel shall not eat in it, in the
קרבן פסח. Okay, וכל בן נכר לא יאכל בו, vechol ben neichar
lo yochal bo, shall not eat the קרבן פסח. בו bo אינו
אוכל, eino ochel, that's the limiting word. You can't eat the פסח,
אבל אוכל הוא במצה ומרור. aval ochel hu bematzah umaror. He still
has a מצוה of מצה ומרור. matzah umaror. So therefore, I already
knew that as long as there's a מקדש, Mikdash. even if you're
not eating the קרבן פסח, you're eating מצה ומרור. matzah umaror. So
for me, בערב תאכלו מצות ba’erev tochelu matzos tells me it applies
even without a מקדש. Mikdash, And רבי יהודה said no, I needed
two פסוקים to tell me that it applies even nowadays, even without
a מקדש. רבי יהודה כתיב בהאי וכתיב בהאי, Rabbi Yehuda ksiv behai
uksiv behai, one is by ערל ובן נכר, arel uven neichar, one
is by the טמא ושהיה בדרך רחוקה, tamei veshehayah bederech rechokah, and
I need both. So the upshot is that רבי יהודה uses a
פסוק to tell you before פסח, during פסח, after פסח. רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says, I use those פסוקים for other things. I link
חמץ to מצה matzah to tell me חמץ only applies when מצה
matzah applies. But there's another linking in the other direction, which tells
you that as long as there's a throughout your generations when there's
a prohibition of חמץ, the מצוה of מצה matzah applies even after
מקדש, and that's not at all clear in the פסוקים, because the
פסוקים make it sound either it's seven days or it's part of
קרבן פסח. But that there should be a special מצוה on the
first night unrelated to קרבן פסח, that's what we have to learn
out here. Okay, to be continued tomorrow.